I grew up
لقد نشأت
in a very small village in Canada,
في قرية صغيرة في كندا،
and I'm an undiagnosed
وتم تشخيصي بمرض
dyslexic.
صعوبة التعلّم.
I had a really hard time in school.
وقد عانيت بشدة أثناء فترة المدرسة.
In fact, my mother told me eventually
في الواقع، أخبرتني والدتي
that I was the little kid in the village
أنني كنت الطفل الصغير في القرية
who cried all the way to school.
الذي يبكي طوال الطريق إلى المدرسة.
I ran away.
وقد هربت.
I left when I was 25 years old to go to Bali,
عند بلوغي سن 25 ذهبت إلى بالي.
and there I met my incredible wife, Cynthia,
وإلتقيت هناك بزوجتي الرائعة، سينثيا،
and together, over 20 years,
وقمنا سوياً خلال 20 سنة،
we built an amazing jewelry business.
بتأسيس عمل تجاري في المجوهرات.
It was a fairy tale, and then we retired.
لقد كان خرافة في النجاح، ثم تقاعدنا.
Then she took me to see a film
وقد اصطحبتني لمشاهدة فلم
that I really didn't want to see.
لم أكن أرغب في مشاهدته.
It ruined my life --
لقد دمّر حياتي--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"The Inconvenient Truth" and Mr. Gore.
فلم "الحقيقة المزعجة" للسيد آل غور.
I have four kids,
لديّ أربعة أطفال،
and even if part of what he says is true,
ورغماً عن أن جزء مما يقوله صحيح،
they're not going to have the life that I had.
من أنهم لن يعيشوا الحياة التي عشتها أنا.
And I decided at that moment
فقد قررت في تلك اللحظة
that I would spend the rest of my life
بأنني سأقضي بقية عمري
doing whatever I could
أفعل ما بوسعي
to improve their possibilities.
لتعزيز فرص نجاحهم.
So here's the world,
إذاً، ها هو العالم،
and here we are in Bali.
ونحن هنا في بالي.
It's a tiny, little island --
إنها جزيرة صغيرة جداً --
60 miles by 90 miles.
طولها 60 ميلا وعرضها 90 ميلا.
It has an intact Hindu culture.
وتتميز بثقافة هندوسية بكر.
Cynthia and I were there.
كنت أنا و سينثيا هناك.
We had had a wonderful life there,
عشنا حياة رائعة هناك،
and we decided to do something unusual.
وقررنا أن نفعل شيئا غير إعتيادي.
We decided to give back
لقد قررنا المساهمة
locally.
للمجتمع المحلي.
And here it is: it's called the Green School.
وهاهي المساهمة، تسمى بالمدرسة الخضراء.
I know it doesn't look like a school,
أعرف أنها لا تشبه المدرسة،
but it is something we decided to do,
لكنها شيئ قررنا إقامته،
and it is extremely,
وهي خضراء جداً،
extremely green.
خضراء للغاية.
The classrooms have no walls.
فصول الدراسة بلا جدران.
The teacher is writing on a bamboo blackboard.
ويكتب المعلّم على سبورة خيزران سوداء.
The desks are not square.
الأدراج ليست مربعة.
At Green School, the children are smiling --
في المدرسة الخضراء، يبتسم الأطفال --
an unusual thing for school, especially for me.
شئ غير معتاد في المدارس، خصوصاً بالنسبة لي.
And we practice holism.
ونحن نمارس الكلانية (عكس مرض التوحّد).
And for me it's just the idea
وبالنسبة لي هي مجرد فكرة
that, if this little girl
أنه إذا تخرجت هذه الفتاة الصغيرة
graduates as a whole person,
كشخص كامل،
chances are
فان الفرص المتاحة
she'll demand a whole world --
لتطالب بكل العالم --
a whole world --
كل العالم --
to live on.
لأن تعيش به.
Our children spend 181 days
يقضي أطفالنا 181 يوماً
going to school in a box.
في الذهاب لمدارس في صندوق.
The people that built my school
الناس الذين بنوا مدرستي
also built the prison and the insane asylum
أيضاً قاموا ببناء السجن والمصحة العقلية
out of the same materials.
من نفس مواد البناء.
So if this gentleman
إذاً فاذا تلقى هذا الشخص
had had a holistic education,
تعليماً شاملاً،
would he be sitting there?
هل كان سيكون هناك جالساً؟
Would he have had more possibilities in his life?
هل كانت لتتاح له فرصاً أكثر في هذه الحياة؟
The classrooms have natural light.
للفصول الدراسية إضاءة طبيعية.
They're beautiful. They're bamboo.
إنها جميلة. إنها من الخيزران.
The breeze passes through them.
يمر النسيم عبر الفصول.
And when the natural breeze isn't enough,
وحينما لا يكون النسيم الطبيعي كافياً،
the kids deploy bubbles,
يستخدم الأطفال فقاعات،
but not the kind of bubbles you know.
لكن ليس نوع الفقاعات التي تعرفونها.
These bubbles are made from natural cotton
هذه الفقاعات مصنوعة من القطن الطبيعي
and rubber from the rubber tree.
والمطاط من أشجار المطاط الطبيعي.
So we basically turned the box
قمنا في الأساس بتحويل الصندوق
into a bubble.
إلى فقاعة.
And these kids know
ويعلم أؤلئك الأطفال
that painless climate control
أن التحكم المؤلم في المناخ
may not be
ربما ليس
part of their future.
جزء من مستقبلهم.
We pay the bill at the end of the month,
نحن ندفع الفاتورة في نهاية الشهر،
but the people that are really going to pay the bill
لكن من سيدفعون الفاتورة حقاً
are our grandchildren.
هم أحفادنا.
We have to teach the kids
ينبغي أن نعلّم الأطفال
that the world is not indestructible.
أن العالم ليس قابلاً للتدمير.
These kids did a little graffiti on their desks,
قام هؤلاء الأطفال بكتابة صغيرة على ادراجهم،
and then they signed up for two extra courses.
ثم إنضموا لمنهجين دراسيين إضافية.
The first one was called sanding
كان الاول يسمى الترميل (التعامل مع الرمل)،
and the second one was called re-waxing.
وسُمّي الثاني بإعادة التصفيف.
But since that happened,
ومنذ أن حدث ذلك،
they own those desks.
إمتلكوا تلك الأدراج.
They know they can control their world.
وهم يعلمون أنه يمكنهم التحكم بعوالمهم.
We're on the grid. We're not proud of it.
نحن موصولون على شبكة كهرباء. ولكنا غير فخورون بها.
But an amazing alternative energy company in Paris
لكن شركة طاقة بديلة في باريس
is taking us off the grid with solar.
تأخذنا خارج الشبكة عبر الطاقة الشمسية.
And this thing
وهذا الشئ
is the second vortex to be built in the world,
هو ثاني دوامة يتم بناؤها في العالم،
in a two-and-a-half meter drop on a river.
بضخ مترين ونصف من الماء على نهر.
When the turbine drops in,
وعندما تضخ التوربينات،
it will produce 8,000 watts of electricity,
ستنتج طاقة كهربائية قدرها 8000 واط
day and night.
طوال الصباح والمساء.
And you know what these are.
وتعلمون ماهية هذه الأشياء.
There's nowhere to flush.
لا يوجد مكان للسحب.
And as long as we're taking our waste
وطالما نقوم بأخذ مخلفاتنا
and mixing it with a huge amount of water --
ونمزجها بكمية كبيرة من المياة--
you're all really smart, just do the math.
أنتم جميعاً اذكياء، قوموا بالحساب.
How many people times how much water.
عدد الناس مضروباً في كمية المياة.
There isn't enough water.
لا توجد مياه كافية.
These are compost toilets,
هذه مراحيض أسمدة.
and nobody at the school wanted to know about them,
ولا أحد في المدرسة أراد أن يعرف المزيد عنها
especially the principal.
خصوصاً المدير.
And they work. People use them. People are okay.
وهم يعملون. يستخدمها الناس. والجميع بخير.
It's something you should think about doing.
وهو شئ ينبغي أن تفكروا بعمله.
Not many things didn't work.
لا تفشل الكثير من الأشياء بل تنجح
The beautiful canvas and rubber skylights
مناور القماش والمطاط الجميلة
got eaten by the sun in six months.
أكلها لهيب الشمس خلال 6 شهور.
We had to replace them with recyclable plastic.
توجّب علينا إحلالها ببلاستيك قابل للتدوير.
The teachers dragged giant PVC whiteboards
سحب المعلمون سبورات بيضاء ضخمة من البلاستيك
into the classrooms.
داخل الفصول الدراسية،
So we had some good ideas:
وكان لدينا بعض الأفكار الجيدة.
we took old automobile windshields, put paper behind them
أخذنا الزجاج الأمامي لسيارات قديمة، ووضعنا أوراق خلفها
and created the first alternative
وصنعنا أول بديل
to the whiteboard.
للسبورة البيضاء.
Green School sits in south-central Bali,
تقع المدرسة الخضراء في منتصف جنوب بالي،
and it's on 20 acres
على مساحة 20 فدانا
of rolling garden.
من الخضرة والحدائق.
There's an amazing river traveling through it,
وهناك نهر رائع يجري خلالها،
and you can see there
وأنتم ترون هناك
how we manage to get across the river.
كيف نعبر النهر.
I met a father the other day; he looked a little crazed.
لقد قابلت أحد الآباء ، وقد بدى مثل المجنون.
I said, "Welcome to Green School."
قلت له " مرحباً بك في المدرسة الخضراء."
He said, "I've been on an airplane for 24 hours."
فقال : "كنت أسافر طوال 24 على الطائرة."
I asked him, "Why?"
وسألته : "لماذا"؟
He said, "I had a dream once about a green school,
فرد، " حلمت ذات مرة بمدرسة خضراء،
and I saw a picture of this green school,
وقد رأيت صورة لهذه المدرسة الخضراء،
I got on an airplane.
فركبت الطائرة فوراً.
In August I'm bringing my sons."
وخلال شهر أغسطس سأجلب أبنائي."
This was a great thing.
كان هذا شيئاً رائعاً.
But more than that,
لكن أكثر من ذلك،
people are building green houses around Green School,
يبنى الناس منازل خضراء حول المدرسة الخضراء،
so their kids can walk to school on the paths.
بحيث يستطيع أبناؤهم المشي إلى المدرسة عبر المسارات.
And people are bringing their green industries,
ويجلب الناس مصانعهم الخضراء،
hopefully their green restaurants,
ونأمل بالحصول على مطاعم خضراء،
to the Green School.
داخل المدرسة الخضراء.
It's becoming a community.
إنه يتطور ليصبح مجتمعاً كاملاً.
It's becoming a green model.
ويصبح نموذجاً أخضراً.
We had to look at everything.
ينبغي أن نراعي كل شئ.
No petrochemicals in the pavement.
لا بتروكيماويات في الرصيف.
No pavement.
لا يوجد رصيف.
These are volcanic stones laid by hand.
هناك صخور بركانية مرصوصة يدوياً.
There are no sidewalks.
لا يوجد ممشى جانبي.
The sidewalks are gravel. They flood when it rains,
الأرصفة من الحصى التي تظهر عندما تمطر
but they're green.
لكنها خضراء.
This is the school buffalo.
هذا هو جاموس المدرسة.
He's planning to eat that fence for dinner.
وهو يخطط لأكل ذلك السور لعشاءه.
All the fences at Green School are green.
من الخضرة نصنع كل الأسوار في المدرسة الخضراء.
And when the kindergarten kids
وحينما قام أطفال رياض الأطفال
recently moved their gate,
مؤخراً بنقل بوابتهم،
they found out the fence was made out of tapioca.
وجدوا أن السور كان مصنوعاً من التابيوكا.
They took the tapioca roots up to the kitchen,
أقتفوا أثر جذور التابيوكا حتى المطبخ،
sliced them thinly and made delicious chips.
قاموا بتقطيعها لأجزاء صغيرة وصنعوا رقائق لذيذة.
Landscaping.
المناظر الطبيعية.
We manage to keep the garden that was there
قررنا الإبقاء على الحدائق التي كانت هناك
running right up to the edge of each of the classrooms.
كما حتى حافة كل الفصول الدراسية.
We dropped them gently in.
قمنا بسحبها بسلاسة.
We made space for these guys
وافسحنا مجالا لهؤلاء
who are Bali's last black pigs.
الذين هم آخر الخنازير السوداء في بالي.
And the school cow
وتحاول بقرة المدرسة
is trying to figure out
معرفة كيفية
how to replace the lawnmower
إحلال جزازة العشب
on the playing field.
على الملعب.
These young ladies
هؤلاء الفتيات اليافعات
are living in a rice culture,
يعيشون في ثقافة الأرز،
but they know something that few people know in a rice culture.
لكنهم يعرفون شيئاً عن ثقافة الأرز يعرفه القليلون.
They know how to plant organic rice,
إنهن يعرفن كيفية زراعة الارز العضوي،
they know how to look after it,
ويعرفن كيفية رعايته،
they know how to harvest and they know how to cook it.
ويعرفن كيفية حصاده وكذلك كيفية طبخه.
They're part of the rice cycle
إنهن جزء من دورة الأرز.
and these skills will be valuable
وهذه المهارات ستكون ذات قيمة
for them in their future.
لهن في مستقبلهن.
This young man is picking organic vegetables.
يقوم هذا الشاب بقطف الخضروات العضوية.
We feed 400 people lunch every day
نحن نقدم وجبة غداء ل 400 شخص يومياً.
and it's not a normal lunch. There's no gas.
وهو ليس بغداء إعتيادي...بدون غازات.
Local Balinese women
تطبخ نساء بالي المحليات
cook the food on sawdust burners
الطعام على مواقد نشارة الخشب
using secrets that only their grandmothers know.
بأستخدام أسرار لا يعرفها سوى جداتهن.
The food is incredible.
الطعام شهي جداً
Green School is a place of pioneers,
المدرسة الخضراء هي مكان للرواد،
local and global.
محلياً وعالمياً.
And it's a kind of microcosm
وهي نسخة مصغرة
of the globalized world.
من عالم متعولم.
The kids are from 25 countries.
هؤلاء الأطفال قادمون من 25 دولة.
When I see them together,
حينما أراهم سوياً
I know that they're working out
أعرف أنهم يخططون
how to live in the future.
لكيفية العيش في المستقبل.
Green School is going into its third year
المدرسة الخضراء تدخل في عامها الثالث
with 160 children.
بعدد 160 طفلاً.
It's a school where you do learn reading --
إنها مدرسة حيث تستطيع القراءة --
one of my favorites --
أحد أفضل هواياتي --
writing -- I was bad at it --
الكتابة -- كنت سيئ في الكتابة --
arithmetic.
الحساب.
But you also learn other things.
لكنك تتعلم أشياء أخرى.
You learn bamboo building.
تتعلم تسلق أشجار الخيزران.
You practice
وتتدرب
ancient Balinese arts.
على فنون بالي القديمة.
This is called mud wrestling in the rice fields.
هذا يسمى بمصارعة الطين في حقول الأرز.
The kids love it.
يحبها الأطفال.
The mothers aren't quite convinced.
لكن الأمهات غير مقتنعات إلى حد كبير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We've done a lot of outrageous things in our lives,
لقد فعلنا الكثير من الأشياء الفاحشة في حياتنا،
and we said, okay, local, what does "local" mean?
وقد قلنا، حسناً لنهتم بالأشياء المحلية، لكن مالذي تعنيه محلية؟
Local means
المحلية تعني
that 20 percent of the population of the school
أن 20% من تلاميذ المدرسة
has to be Balinese,
ينبغي أن يكونوا من بالي.
and this was a really big commitment.
وكان هذا إلتزاماً كبيراً جداً.
And we were right.
وكنا على حق.
And people are coming forward
حيث يأتي الناس قدماً
from all over the world
من كل أنحاء العالم
to support the Balinese Scholarship Fund,
لدعم صندوق المنح الدراسية في بالي،
because these kids will be Bali's next green leaders.
لأن هؤلاء الأطفال سيكونوا الجيل القادم للقادة في بالي
The teachers are as diverse
والمعلمون متنوعون
as the student body,
كما هو حال التلاميذ
and the amazing thing
والشئ المدهش
is that volunteers are popping up.
هو أن المتطوعون يأتون
A man came from Java
جاء رجل من جافا
with a new kind of organic agriculture.
بنوع جديد من الزراعة العضوية
A woman came from Africa with music.
وجاءت إمرأة من أفريقيا بالموسيقى
And together these volunteers and the teachers
المتطوعون والمعلمون مع بعضهم البعض
are deeply committed
ملتزمون بشدة
to creating a new generation
بخلق جيل جديد
of global, green leaders.
من القادة العالميون الخضر.
The Green School effect --
تؤثر المدرسة الخضراء --
we don't know what it is.
نحن لا نعرف ماهية التأثير
We need someone to come and study it.
نحتاج لشخص ما أن يأتي ويدرس التأثيرات
But what's happening, our learning-different kids --
لكن ما يحدث، أن أطفالنا الذين يعانون من --
dyslexic --
عسر القراءة--
we've renamed them prolexic --
قمنا بإعادة تسميتهم بقادرون على القراءة
are doing well in these beautiful, beautiful classrooms.
وهم ينجحون بشدة في هذه الفصول الدراسية الرائعة جداً.
And all the kids are thriving.
وجميع الأطفال يزدهرون.
And how did we do all this?
كيف نفعل كل هذا؟
On giant grass.
على الملاعب العشبية الضخمة.
It's bamboo.
إنها الخيزران
It comes out of the ground like a train.
إنها تأتي من الأرض مثل القطار
It grows as high as a coconut tree in two months
وتنمو لتصبح بعلو شجرة جوز الهند خلال شهرين.
and three years later it can be harvested
ويمكن حصدها بعد ثلاث سنوات
to build buildings like this.
لتشييد مباني مثل هذا.
It's as strong and dense as teak
إنها قوية وكثيفة مثل خشب التيك.
and it will hold up any roof.
وتستطيع تحمل أي سطح.
When the architects came, they brought us these things,
حينما جاء المعماريون، جلبوا لنا هذه الأشياء،
and you've probably seen things like this.
وعلى الأرجح أنكم رأيتم شيئاً كهذا.
The yellow box was called the administration complex.
الصندوق الأصفر يسمى بمجمع الإدارة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We squashed it, we rethought it,
قمنا بسحقها وأعدنا التفكير بشأنها،
but mainly we renamed it
لكننا أعدنا تسميتها بصفة عامة --
"the heart of school,"
بقلب المدرسة.
and that changed everything forever.
وقد غيّر هذا كل شئ إلى الأبد
It's a double helix.
إنها الحلزون المزدوج.
It has administrators in it
ولديها مدراء داخلها
and many, many other things.
والكثير الكثير من الأشياء الأخرى.
And the problem of building it --
ومشكلة تشييدها --
when the Balinese workers
حينما رآى عمال البناء
saw long reams of plans,
الباليون رزمة طويلة من الخطط،
they looked at them and said, "What's this?"
نظروا إليهم وقالوا: "ما هذا؟"
So we built big models.
لذا فقد بنينا نماذج ضخمة.
We had them engineered by the engineers.
وتم هندستها بواسطة مهندسين.
And Balinese carpenters like this
والنجارون الباليون مثل هذا
measured them with their bamboo rulers,
قاموا بقياسها بمساطر الخيزران
selected the bamboo and built the buildings
أختاروا الخيزران وشيدوا المباني
using age-old techniques,
باستخدام أساليب قديمة
mostly by hand.
يدوياً في أغلب الأوقات.
It was chaos.
لقد كانت فوضى
And the Balinese carpenters want to be as modern as we do,
وأراد النجارون الباليون أن يكونوا عصريين كما نحن،
so they use metal scaffolding
لذا استخدموا السقالات المعدنية
to build the bamboo building
لتشييد مباني الخيزران
and when the scaffolding came down,
وحينما تم إنزال السقالات المعدنية،
we realized that we had a cathedral,
أدركنا أن لدينا كاتدرائية،
a cathedral to green,
كاتدرائية خضراء
and a cathedral to green education.
و كاتدرائية تعليم أخضر.
The heart of school has seven kilometers
لقلب المدرسة سبعة كيلومترات
of bamboo in it.
من الخيزران بداخله
From the time the foundations were finished,
منذ وقت التأسيس وحتى الإنتهاء،
in three months it had roofs and floors.
خلال ثلاثة شهور أكملنا السقوف والأرضيات.
It may not be the biggest bamboo building in the world,
ربما لا تكون أكبر مبنى من الخيزران في العالم،
but many people believe
لكن يعتقد الكثير من الناس
that it's the most beautiful.
أنها الأكثر جمالاً
Is this doable in your community?
هل هذا ممكن الحدوث في مجتمعكم؟
We believe it is.
نحن نعتقد ذلك
Green School is a model we built for the world.
المدرسة الخضراء هي النموذج الذي نبني عليه للعالم.
It's a model we built for Bali.
إنها النموذج الذي بنينا عليه لبالي.
And you just have to follow these simple, simple rules:
ويتوجب علينا فقط إتباع هذه القواعد البسيطة جداً:
be local,
كن محلي الطابع،
let the environment lead
دع البيئة تقود المسألة
and think about
وفكّر حول
how your grandchildren might build.
كيف سيبني أحفادك.
So, Mr. Gore, thank you.
إذاً، السيد آل غور، شكراً لك.
You ruined my life,
لقد دمرت حياتي،
but you gave me an incredible future.
لكنك أعطيتني مستقبل مذهل.
And if you're interested in being involved
وإن كنت مهتم بالمشاركة
in finishing Green School
في تكملة المدرسة الخضراء
and building the next 50 around the world,
وبناء ال 50 مدرسة القادمة حول العالم،
please come and see us.
أرجو أن تأتي لزيارتنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)